Joshua Johanson

The most time consuming part this week was the basic word order.  I think part of the problem is
that word order that deviates from the normal only happens in context and sounds awkward outside
of context.  I took the example you gave me of “Cats he like” as asked some native English speakers
if it were grammatical.  Not one non-linguistics person told me it was grammatical.  However, with
the more complicated sentence of “The refuges that were affected by Hurricane Katrina I really hope
get a good home” they all said it was grammatical.  This is frustrating because it is the same
concept, and we would expect it to hold true regardless of the length of the sentence.  The same thing
happened with my Italian speaker.  Some sentences he said that the verb and subject could be
switched around and some sentences he said couldn’t.  (He also said “Cats he likes” is
ungrammatical in English, even after I tried to explain to him that it was.)  I know I have heard more
grammatical variety than what he said.  He even said that some of the things my book said was right
was wrong.  Even though it doesn’t make sense to me, I still went with what he said.  
		
The determiners were just annoying.  There were 22 determiners including demonstratives.  Add
that to the 38 pronouns and you get over a quarter of your sentences dealing with vocabulary.  I did
combine some of the sentences at the end, but it was just repetitive work.  I knew determiners could
are often used with proper names, but it was good to learn when and why.  Apparently cities are
never used with determiners.  Other than that, determiners were pretty easy.

Imperatives were a challenge.  It has four forms; you single informal, you single formal, you plural
informal, and you plural formal. It was tricky, because the you single informal form was different
from the other ones, and had a form similar to the regular 3rd person tense.  I had to construct my
examples very carefully to make sure that the grammar checker didn’t mix up the two forms.  Since
the other three forms were pretty similar, I decided to only show the one differing in number and the
one differing in person.  Negatives and direct objects were also treated differently with imperatives. 
Again, these examples had to be constructed very carefully to make sure that a grammatical
example from another person and tense wouldn’t be marked ungrammatical.

Embedded and relative clauses were very similar to archaic prescriptive English (“The man with
whom I work ...” instead of “The man who I work with ...”) I think this is because many of these
prescriptive rules came from Italian.  The only difference with embedded clause is the “that” is never
optional in declarative clauses.

Adjectives were straight-forward.  They could come either before or after the noun and had to agree
with it.  

I also made some changes to the grammar I had turned in last week.  The main reason is that I was
able to go over some of them with my native speaker, and found I was wrong. Other sentences I
changed to read better.  I also added the demonstrative pronouns that I had left out earlier.  

It was interesting some of the changes my native speaker made.  He said you couldn’t say “la
pilota”, even though that phrase occurs 794 times on Italian pages on the web.  He said that my
negatives were opposite what my book told me.  I think it is hard to say what is right when you just
usually stick with the standard way of doing things.  I changed that to fit what he said was right.  I
think the actual practice varies from region to region.
He didn’t seem to like using the dative form of loro.  He kept wanting to put it as a preposition (“I
gave the books to them” instead of “I gave them the books.”) That is what I do, when I speak
Italian.  It is kind of unsettling to think that all pronouns can go into dative form except for loro,
even though the book says it can.  I just decided to drop it from my test suite.

I learned a lot.  I am glad I am doing Italian because there are quite a few Italian speakers to help
you go over your sentences.  I think that helped me feel more confident in my sentences.  I would
hate to spend lots of time making my grammar licence an ungrammatical sentence.  (Even though I
am sure I will.)  I don’t think I have any more questions other than the ones I have previously
mentioned.  I would like to get a second opinion, mainly because I think his judgement started to get
kind of clouded after having to make so many grammatical judgements.  I am also very excited to
start working on the actual grammar. 
