Ryan Georgi
Ling 567: Grammar Engineering


LAB 2: Test Suite

------------------- TRANSCRIPTION -------------------------

The grammar I am using uses the IPA for representing the sounds of Modern Standard Arabic (MSA). Below is a chart showing how I will translate to ASCII (according to the ascii-IPA translation document found here:
http://www.kirshenbaum.net/IPA/ascii-ipa.pdf)

                     Plosive   Fricative  Affricate  Liquid  Nasal
labial                   b            w                         m
labiodental                       f
dental       plain    t  d        s   z               l
           emphatic   t. d.       s.  (z.)
interdental  plain                T   D
           emphatic                   D.
alveolar                          s^ (z^)     j       r         n
palatal                               y
velar                 k (g)       x   g.
uvular                q
pharyngeal                        h.  '
glottal               ?           h

(Here are the notable changes:)

Θ = T
ð = D
˙ (diacritic dot) = .
? = ?
alveolar diacritic = ^

----------------- MORPHOPHONOLOGY -------------------------

Although Arabic has relatively involved morphophonology, it is mostly quite predictable. For instance, in my research the definite article /?al-/ is rarely seen as such, since it often loses the /?a-/ when post-vocalic and the -l- aligns with the consonant when it is one of a handful of 'solar' consonants. I will provide a regularized line in the IGT to make life easier when I go to implement this.

--------------------------- WORD ORDER ---------------------


The most basic (and common) word order in arabic is:

(1) V S COMP

...when no COMP is needed/present, this is also just

(1b) V S

However, since nouns show agreement (more on this later) with the verb, the word order is somewhat flexible. In addition to the above, the following alternative is not uncommon:

(2) S V COMP

Though there is technically no restriction on (1), it is apparantly most commonly used in newsprint for "event-oriented" messages, with focus on who did what, and how. (2) is common for providing incidental background for a known S.

V COMP S

Also occurs infrequently, and its subject must be indefinite and the complement definite.

And since nouns can often be expressed as pronomial affixes, the following forms are also acceptable:

V COMP

V

Finally, the 'to be' copula can also be expressed as a affix, so:

S COMP

is also acceptable in this case.

I will address word order with respect to adjectives later.

---------------- PRONOUNS -----------------------------

In MSA, personal pronouns can either be free-standing, or bound clitics on the verb. The free-standing personal pronouns vary in person, number, and gender, and are only found in the nominative. In this case they are rarely found with a verb since the verb generally shows agreement. When they do appear free-standing, their meaning is usually that of the copula 'be', e.g.:

?ana ?inkili:zi:yun
I    English
'I am English'

(There are a few exceptions where this can be used on its own, notably as a 'linking' particle when a sentence such as the above might be ambiguous between an NP and full sentence, such as 'the manager responsible for this' and 'the manager is the person responsible for this')

The clitic form may be attached to NPs to denote posession, part-whole relations, and a verbal noun's agent or patient (which is actually ambiguous; /qatlu-hu/ or 'his killing' can be interpreted to be either active or passive).

Demonstrative pronouns, on the other hand, are always free-standing and can be both nominal and adjectival, and are inflected for both gender and number. When they are used adjectivally, their head noun must be definite.

---------------- THE NP --------------------------------

The noun phrase in MSA is inflected for definiteness, case (though more precisely syntactic function), and feminine gender (nouns not given the feminine ending are generally masculine, though there are exceptions on either side).

--------------- AGREEMENT / ADJECTIVES --------------------

In treating NPs in my test suite, I will be paying particular attention to agreement, as nouns must agree with adjectives not only in number, gender, case, and definiteness.

Verbs also agree with their subjects, though, interestingly, how much depends on the order of S and V.

...agreement appears to be quite complicated, however, (for instance, how the adjectival plural is formed depends on whether the modified noun is animate or not) so, I need to find other sources to validate what I've drawn thus far. So far in my agreement examples, I'm trying to only use human examples drawn from my grammar.

In some of these, the IGT did not make it clear what was happening morphologically, so occasionally I have -??? when I need to investigate further.

--------------- ARGUMENT OPTIONALITY ---------------------

As discussed in the PRONOUNS section, the personal pronouns are rarely seen free-standing and are more often seen as pronomial affixes. Pronomial subjects are usually left out because of agreement on the verb, and while verbs do not show agreement for objects generally, they can incorporate pronomial objects.


--------------- CASE ------------------------------------

Nouns in MSA have three cases, Nominative, Accusative and Genitive. (Though the names for these cases have little to do with their "traditional" usage in European languages) How these cases are marked on the noun are determined by their definiteness and which of two declensions they fall in.

Both declensions have three suffixes for definite nouns. The first, called the Triptotes, have only one for the all indefinites, while the diptotes have one for indefinites in the nominative and another for the accusative and genitive.

It should be noted that case markings are not traditionally written in standard orthography and appear to be optional in spoken MSA, but I will include them systematically, as it should be easier to create rules for optional deletion than for optional insertion.

