Modules page choices:
In my first modules page run I indicated that the Hebrew conjunction "w" is an affix. Since I also indicated that phrases can be coordinated in Hebrew I got a script error since an affix is incompatible with phrase coordination. I changed the designation of "w" from affix to word to avoid the error. The "w" is probably a clitic rather than an affix. Still, designating it as a word means that it is treated as an independent unit. At this point, all the sentences in the test suite that contain the coordination phenomenon fail to parse because in them the "w" is attached to the first word of the last coordinand. So I will need to find a solution for this somehow.All my other choices were more or less straightforward. 

My first parses worked as expected except for coordination. I am getting more parses than I think I want, but this requires careful analysis, which I cannot do justice to right now.

ITSDB Results:
The coverage on my automatically generated lexicon was 0. Once I added to the lexcion words based on the lab4 instructions (21 additional noun entries, 19 additional pronoun entries,3 additional intransitive verb entries, 5 additional transitive verb entries, and 1 additional neg-ad entry), the coverage improved to 10.8% (17.9 for i-length [0..5] and 0 for i-length [5..10]). The overgeneartion is 3.8% [5.9 for i-length [0..5] and 0 for i-length [5..10]). This includes also the benefit of my having corrected several typos in the test suite.

 I think that the biggest bang for the buck will come from figuring out how to handle the "clitics". There are tons of words now which are not recognized because there is a clitic attached to them as a prefix. One option is to separate them from the words they prefix in the test suite and assume the preprocessor does that, which is not a far fetched assumption. Handling it within the lexicon may also be an option. But admittedly, given all the technical hurdles I spent hours and hours jumping through, I haven't had the chance to do a proper analysis yet.
